<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://vinayakpathak.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://vinayakpathak.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-11-18T05:57:56+00:00</updated><id>https://vinayakpathak.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">What do Newton’s laws really say?</title><link href="https://vinayakpathak.github.io/blog/2024/newton/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What do Newton’s laws really say?"/><published>2024-11-13T23:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-13T23:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://vinayakpathak.github.io/blog/2024/newton</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://vinayakpathak.github.io/blog/2024/newton/"><![CDATA[<p>I recently read this Feynman quote:</p> <blockquote> <p>Study hard what interests you the most in the most undisciplined, irreverent and original manner possible.</p> </blockquote> <p>And decided to express some long-suppressed irreverance on this blog: I think Newton did a terrible job summarizing his work in terms of those three famous laws of motion. For reference, here are the three laws (from Wikipedia):</p> <ol> <li>A body remains at rest, or in motion at a constant speed in a straight line, except insofar as it is acted upon by a force.</li> <li>At any instant of time, the net force on a body is equal to the body’s acceleration multiplied by its mass or, equivalently, the rate at which the body’s momentum is changing with time.</li> <li>If two bodies exert forces on each other, these forces have the same magnitude but opposite directions.</li> </ol> <p>Let’s first start with the obvious issue here. The first law sounds like a weaker form of the second law? The second law already says \(F = ma\). If you assume \(F=0\), then as long as the body exists (and thus has non-zero mass), the only possibility is that \(a = 0\). And by the definition of acceleration, \(a = 0\) implies that the velocity does not change. So law #1 is actually implied by law #2.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="physics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[newton]]></summary></entry></feed>