<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://vinayakpathak.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://vinayakpathak.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-11-27T05:50:08+00:00</updated><id>https://vinayakpathak.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">What do Newton’s laws really say?</title><link href="https://vinayakpathak.github.io/blog/2024/newton/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What do Newton’s laws really say?"/><published>2024-11-13T23:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-13T23:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://vinayakpathak.github.io/blog/2024/newton</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://vinayakpathak.github.io/blog/2024/newton/"><![CDATA[<p>I recently read this Feynman quote:</p> <blockquote> <p>Study hard what interests you the most in the most undisciplined, irreverent and original manner possible.</p> </blockquote> <p>And decided to express some long-suppressed irreverance on this blog: Newton’s laws of motion are a piece of terrible writing. They do not really encapsulate the research that Newton had actually done. If I was a coauthor of the paper with him, I would write a comment in red in the overleaf. If this was a github pull request, I would refuse to merge it until the laws were rewritten. For reference, here are the laws from Wikipedia:</p> <ol> <li>A body remains at rest, or in motion at a constant speed in a straight line, except insofar as it is acted upon by a force.</li> <li>At any instant of time, the net force on a body is equal to the body’s acceleration multiplied by its mass or, equivalently, the rate at which the body’s momentum is changing with time.</li> <li>If two bodies exert forces on each other, these forces have the same magnitude but opposite directions.</li> </ol> <p>Let’s first start with the obvious issue here. The first law sounds like a weaker form of the second law? The second law already says \(F = ma\). If you assume \(F=0\), then as long as the body exists (and thus has non-zero mass), the only possibility is that \(a = 0\). And by the definition of acceleration, \(a = 0\) implies that the velocity does not change. So law #1 is actually implied by law #2. This is like if there was a second rule of fight club that said all talking was prohibited. Then the first rule—do not talk about fight club—would merely be a special case of the second rule. I can understand wanting to draw attention to a specific consequence of a law you formulated. For example, just saying \(F=ma\) may not always immediately convey to the reader all of its consequences, and you may want to draw their attention to how the absence of force means velocity does not change. But in today’s parlance, such a statement would be considered a corollary and I wouldn’t mind if law #1 was actually stated as a corollary.</p> <p>The second issue is more subtle but also bigger. To explain, I need to first take a step back. The thinking back then was that motion was the most fundamental thing to explain and the whole universe was simply a large number of tiny things moving around. Sometimes the tiny things got together and formed big things and other times they remained tiny, but the belief was that any phenomenon could be explained by the exact motion of the big and small things constituting it. This program did appear to be successful for a long time. The movements of celestial objects were explained, a fairly reasonable theory of electricity was formulated that relied on charged particles moving under electrostatic forces, and even phenomena like heat and cold were explained using the motion of tiny molecules bumping into each other.</p> <p>So if we put ourselves into Newton’s shoes and try to formulate a theory of motion, the task at hand is this: can you formulate a theory that can predict the trajectories of objects that are moving around? You see some objects in space, and you are allowed to measure any properties of the objects and the space they are in, and with this information you should be able to predict where the objects will be at each point in time in the future. Newton’s claim was that all you needed to do was to measure the object’s mass and the force acting on it and that would tell you its acceleration and you could integrate that twice to get its position. And now I can state my second issue with the laws: up until now, force and mass are both made up quantities and thus the first two laws have basically no content! Or in other words, if the first two laws were all you were equipped with, and you saw a new kind of trajectory being followed by a collection of objects, you could simiply “explain” it by fitting whatever \(F\) and \(m\) result in that particular trajectory. Suppose you came up with some \(F\) and \(m\) and later on you observed some other collection objects following another kind of trajectories, you could just say that this time the \(F\) and \(m\) followed a different set of equations. In other words, there are no trajectories that are ruled out by these laws. It doesn’t exactly seem to qualify to be a law if it allows every possible behaviour, does it?</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="physics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[newton]]></summary></entry></feed>